<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Tanfield Railway</string>

    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>

    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>

    <!-- TODO: Remove or change this placeholder text -->
    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>
    <string name="title_activity_scan">ScanActivity</string>

    <string name="LambtonRailwayDescription">In the 1860s The Earl of Durham, Lord Lambton, made an agreement with the North Eastern Railway to transport coal over its Durham to Sunderland line, between Penshaw and Sunderland. The Earl of Durham used his own locomotives and waggons all the way from the colliery.

Because passenger trains also worked on the line, the Earl of Durham’s trains had to have brake vans at the rear to prevent accidents.

The Earl of Durham’s collieries eventually became part of the massive Lambton Hetton and Joicey Collieries company. In 1947 they became part of the National Coal Board.

This brake van was built in 1946 at the Philadelphia workshops of the Lambton Hetton and Joicey Collieries near Sunderland. It was the last new brake van to be built for the railway, No. 7.

Construction of the van was carried out by apprentice Tom Hardy. This was his ‘test piece’ that he had to complete to qualify as a waggonwright . He built the van in 72 hours and went on to be not only a waggonwright but a successful and well known manager also.

The brake van weighs just under ten tons and the guard riding in the van uses the handbrake to prevent the train snatching or gathering too much speed going downhill.

This brake van was chosen specially to work with the last National Coal Board train between Penshaw and Sunderland in 1967. It was later transferred to the Seaham area where it worked between several collieries and the Londonderry waggon works.

In the 1980s it was made redundant and saved for preservation.

A major overhaul was undertaken in 2014/15 including replacement of much rotten timber. The brake van has now been returned to its 1950s condition.</string>
</resources>
